<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exclamation against Julian, secretary to the Muses with the character of a libeller / by a person of quality.</title>
            <author>Person of quality.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39034</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3844</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14850</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13590921</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13590921</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100664</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39034)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100664)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 788:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exclamation against Julian, secretary to the Muses with the character of a libeller / by a person of quality.</title>
                  <author>Person of quality.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and probable date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Julian may refer to Sir Roger L'Estrange.  Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>L'Estrange, Roger, --  Sir, 1616-1704.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:100664:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN EXCLAMATION Againſt JULIAN, Secretary to the Muſes; With the Character of a LIBELLER.</head>
            <byline>By a Perſon of Quality.</byline>
            <l>THou Common Shore of this Poetick Town,</l>
            <l>Where all our Excrements of Wit are thrown;</l>
            <l>For Sonnet, Satyr, Bawdry, Blaſphemy,</l>
            <l>Are empty'd and disburthen'd all on thee:</l>
            <l>The Cholerick wight, untruffing in a rage,</l>
            <l>Finds thee, and leaves his load upon thy page.</l>
            <l>Thou, <hi>Julian,</hi> (Oh, thou wiſe <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> rather!)</l>
            <l>Doſt from this Dung thy well-pick'd Guineys gather.</l>
            <l>All miſchief's thine: Tranſcribing thou wilt ſtoop</l>
            <l>From lofty <hi>Middleſex,</hi> to lowly <hi>Scroop.</hi>
            </l>
            <lg>
               <l>What times are theſe, when, in that <hi>Hero</hi>'s room</l>
               <l>Bow-bending <hi>Cupid</hi> doth with Ballads come,</l>
               <l>And little <hi>Aſhton</hi> offers to the Bum?</l>
            </lg>
            <l>Can two ſuch <hi>Pigmies</hi> ſuch a wight ſupport?</l>
            <l>Two ſuch <hi>Tom Thumbs</hi> of <hi>Satyr</hi> in a Court!</l>
            <l>Poor <hi>George</hi> grows old; his Muſe worn out of faſhion;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Hoarſly</hi> ſhe ſung <hi>Euphelia</hi>'s Lamentation:</l>
            <l>Leſs art thou helpt by <hi>Dryden</hi>'s Bed-rid Age;</l>
            <l>That Drone has left his Sting upon the Stage.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:100664:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Reſolve me, poor Apoſtate, this main Doubt;</l>
            <l>What hope haſt thou to rub this Summer out?</l>
            <l>Know, and be thankful then; for Providence,</l>
            <l>By me, has ſent thee this Intelligence:</l>
            <l>A Knight there is, if thou canſt gain his Grace,</l>
            <l>Known by the Name of the <hi>Hard-favour'd Face;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>For Proweſs of the Pen renown'd is he;</l>
            <l>From <hi>Don Quixot</hi> deſcended lineally:</l>
            <l>And though, like him, unfortunate he prove,</l>
            <l>Undaunted in Attempts of Wit and Love.</l>
            <l>Of his unfiniſh'd Face, what ſhall I ſay,</l>
            <l>But that 'twas made of <hi>Adam</hi>'s own Red Clay;</l>
            <l>That much, much Oker was on it beſtow'd?</l>
            <l>God's Image 'tis not, but ſome <hi>Indian</hi> God:</l>
            <l>Our Chriſtian Earth can no reſemblance bring</l>
            <l>But Ware of <hi>Portugal</hi> for ſuch a thing.</l>
            <l>Such Carbuncles his fiery Face confeſs,</l>
            <l>As no <hi>Hungarian</hi> Water can redreſs.</l>
            <l>A Face which ſhould he ſee-But Heav'n was kind,</l>
            <l>And, to indulge his Self-love, made him blind.</l>
            <l>He dares not ſtir abroad, for fear to meet</l>
            <l>Curſes of teeming Women in the ſtreet:</l>
            <l>The leaſt could happen from that hidious ſight,</l>
            <l>Is, that they ſhould miſcarry with the fright;</l>
            <l>Heav'n guard'em from the likeneſs of the Knight</l>
            <l>Such is our charming <hi>Strephon</hi>'s outward man:</l>
            <l>His inward parts, Let thoſe deſcribe who can;</l>
            <l>But, by the monthly flow'rs diſcharg'd abroad,</l>
            <l>'Tis full, brim full of Paſtoral and Ode.</l>
            <l>Frewhile he honour'd <hi>Bertha</hi> with his flame;</l>
            <l>And now, he courts no leſs <hi>Louviſa's</hi> Name:</l>
            <l>For, when his Paſſion has been boiling long,</l>
            <l>The ſcum at laſt boils up into a Song:</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:100664:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
And ſure no mortal creature, at one time,</l>
            <l>Was e're ſo far o'regone with Love and Rhyme.</l>
            <l>To his dear ſelf of Poetry he talks;</l>
            <l>His hands and feet are ſcanning as he walks:</l>
            <l>His ſquinting look his pangs of Wit accuſe</l>
            <l>The very ſymptoms of a breeding Muſe:</l>
            <l>And all to gain the great <hi>Louviſa</hi>'s grace;</l>
            <l>But never Pen did pimp for ſuch a Face.</l>
            <l>There's not a Nymph, in City, Town, or Court,</l>
            <l>But <hi>Strephon</hi>'s <hi>Billet Doux</hi>'s have made ſport:</l>
            <l>Still he Loves on; yet ſtill as ſure to miſs</l>
            <l>As they who waſh an <hi>Aethiop</hi>'s face, or his.</l>
            <l>What fate unhappy <hi>Strephon</hi> does attend,</l>
            <l>Never to got a Miſtreſs, or a Friend?</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Strephon</hi> alike both Wit and Fools deteſt;</l>
            <l>Becauſe, like <hi>Aeſop</hi>'s Bat, half Bird, half Beaſt:</l>
            <l>For Fools, to Poetry have no pretence;</l>
            <l>And common Wit ſuppoſes common Senſe:</l>
            <l>Not quite ſo low as Fools, nor quite o'top;</l>
            <l>But hangs between 'em both, and is a Fop.</l>
            <l>His Morals, like his Wit, are motly too:</l>
            <l>He keeps from arrant Knave, with much ado;</l>
            <l>But Vanity and Lying ſo prevail,</l>
            <l>That one grain more of each would turn the ſcale.</l>
            <l>He would be more a Villain, had he time;</l>
            <l>But he's ſo wholly taken up with Rhyme,</l>
            <l>That he miſtakes his Talent: all his care</l>
            <l>Is to be thought a Poet, fine, and fair.</l>
            <l>Small Beer and Gruel, are his meat and drink;</l>
            <l>The Diet he preſcribes himſelf, to think.</l>
            <l>Rhyme next his heart he takes at morning peep;</l>
            <l>Some Love-<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>piſtles at his hour of ſleep:</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:100664:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
So, between Elegy and Ode, we ſee</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Strephon</hi> is in a courſe of Poetry.</l>
            <l>This is the Man ordain'd to do thee good;</l>
            <l>The Pelican, to feed thee with his Blood:</l>
            <l>Thy Wit, thy Poet; nay, thy Friend; for he</l>
            <l>Is fit to be a Friend to none, but Thee.</l>
            <l>Make ſure of him, and of his Muſe betimes;</l>
            <l>For all his Study is hung round with Rhymes:</l>
            <l>Laugh at him, juſtle him, yet ſtill he writes;</l>
            <l>In Rhyme he Challenges, in Rhyme he Fights:</l>
            <l>Charg'd with the laſt, and baſeſt Infamy,</l>
            <l>His bus'neſs is to think what Rhymes to Lye;</l>
            <l>Which found, in fury he retorts again.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Strephon</hi>'s a very Dragon at his Pen:</l>
            <l>His Brother murdred, and his Mother whor'd,</l>
            <l>his Miſtreſs loſt; yet ſtill his Pen's his Sword.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
